Finding Aid for the Arnold Schoenberg Papers PASC-M.0078
UCLA Library Special Collections
Arnold Schoenberg papers
1899-1951
UCLA Library Special Collections
PASC-M.0078
1 linear foot (1 box, 1 flat box)
Collection consists of materials relating mostly to Schoenberg's career at UCLA, including his University of California biography form, and letters to and from Schoenberg, his friends and UCLA colleagues, and his family. Includes miscellaneous photographs, some inscribed, of Schoenberg and others, and clippings relating to his music and career. Also contains a photocopy of the manuscript of Mailied (1899), the original of which is housed in the UCLA Dept. of Special Collections.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9929767783606533
Biography
Arnold Franz Walter Schoenberg was born on Sept. 13, 1874 in Vienna; began composing before he was nine years old; composed the string sextet Verklärte Nacht (1899), which he later scored for string orchestra, and became one of his most popular works; Austrian composers Alban Berg and Anton Webern began studying with him in 1904; his cantata Gurrelieder (begun in 1900) was received enthusiastically at its premiere in 1913; by 1909 he began creating atonal compositions, and in his Opus 25 Piano Suite, he created the first composition based on a row or series of 12 tones; his opera Moses und Aron (begun in 1930) was based on this technique; in 1925 he was invited to direct the master class in musical composition at the Prussian Academy of Arts in Berlin; after the rise of the Nazis, he was dismissed from his post in 1933, and emigrated to the United States via Paris; took a position at the Malkin Conservatory in Boston in November 1933, and then moved to California the following year; after a year as a lecturer at the University of Southern California (1935-36) he taught composition as UCLA from 1936 until his retirement in 1944; he became a U.S. citizen in 1944; continued to create compositions illustrating his mastery of the 12-tone method; died on July 13, 1951 in LA.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of materials relating mostly to Schoenberg's career at UCLA, including his University of California biography form, and letters to and from Schoenberg, his friends and UCLA colleagues, and his family. Includes miscellaneous photographs, some inscribed, of Schoenberg and others, and clippings relating to his music and career. Also contains a photocopy of the manuscript of Mailied (1899), the original of which is housed in the UCLA Dept. of Special Collections.
Composers -- Archives.; Schoenberg, Arnold; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Music--Faculty -- Archives
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Schoenberg and family. Photograph, b&w. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Mailied. Piano score, photocopy. 1899. 3p. Text by Goethe. Orig. MS in URL Special Collections. (Box 1)
- Stein, Leonard. To Pete ?. Correspondence. Dated Dec.11, Feb. 20, Aug. 23 and Dec. 20. No year. (Box 1)
- Petran, Laurence. Organ Variations. Performance notes. Apparently instructions written by Schoenberg. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To David J. Bach. Correspondence. Dated April 4, 1918. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Gertrud. To Franklin D. Murphy. Correspondence, typed. Murphy was UCLA Chancellor. Dated Dec.14, 1962. (Box 1)
- Klemperer, Otto. Letter of Recommendation. Dated Jan 4, 1936. (Box 1)
- Knudsen, Vern O. To Gertrud Schoenberg. Correspondence, photocopy. Dated Aug.7, 1951. (Box 1)
- Rubsamen, Walter H. To Angus E. Taylor. Correspondence. Dated Sept. 29, 1967. Taylor was a UCLA Vice-Chancellor. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Birthday Canons to Carl Engel. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Moses and Aaron. Newspaper review. Munich. 1965. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. UC In Memorium. 1951. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Schoenberg Hall Dedication. Program. 1956. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. UC Biography, photostat. Dated May 14, 1936. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Gertrud. Obituary. Newspaper clipping. Los Angeles. Dated Feb.15, 1967 in Los Angeles Times. (Box 1)
- Shoenberg, Arnold. Memorial Concert. Clipping. (Box 1)
- Taylor, Angus E. To Walter H. Rubsamen. Correspondence. Dated Oct. 5, 1967. Taylor was a UCLA Vice Chancellor. (Box 1)
- Vincent, John. To Arnold Schoenberg. Correspondence. Dated Dec.7, 1949. (Box 1)
- Vincent, John. To Arnold Schoenberg. Correspondence. Dated Jan.16, 1950. (Box 1)
- Vincent, John. To Arnold Schoenberg. Correspondence. Dated Mar. 8, 1950. (Box 1)
- Vincent, John. To Arnold Schoenberg. Correspondence. Dated Apr. 25, 1951. (Box 1)
- Vincent, John. To Baldwin Woods. Letter of Recommendation. Dated Apr. 21, 1950. (Box 1)
- Woods, Baldwin M. To John Vincent. Schoenberg's Honorary Degree. Dated Apr. 18, 1950. (Box 1)
- Manuscript pages. Photograph, b&w. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Photograph, b&w. (Box 1)
- Dedication Concert for Arnold Schoenberg Hall. Program. UCLA. Dated May 15, 1956. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg Music Festival. Program. UCLA. Dates: March 27, April 10 & 24. No year. (Box 1)
- Dedication concert. Newspaper clipping. 1956. From Daily Bruin. Dated May 11, 1956. (Box 1)
- Dedication of Schoenberg Hall. Newspaper clipping. From Daily Bruin. Dated May 14, 1956. (Box 1)
- Prisma (Nr. 4). Journal. 1949. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Copy of Schoenberg's broadcast text. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. List of articles and books by Schoenberg. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To Allen. Correspondence. Dated Jan. 19, 1945. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To Allen. Correspondence. Dated Oct. 4, 1937. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To UC Regents. Correspondence, photocopy. Never sent. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To Emil Hilb. Correspondence. Dated Jun.16, 1951. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To Emil Hilb. Correspondence. Dated Nov. 29, 1939. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To Emil Hilb. Correspondence. No date. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To John Vincent. Correspondence. Dated Apr. 28, 1950. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To John Vincent. Correspondence. Dated Feb. 5, 1950. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To John Vincent. Correspondence. Dated Nov. 2, 1949. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To John Vincent. Correspondence. Dated Nov. 5, 1949. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To John Vincent. Correspondence. No date. Only 3rd page of letter. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To John Vincent. Postcard. Dated Apr. 17, 1951. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To Laurence Petran. Correspondence. Dated Dec. 4, 1946. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To Laurence Petran. Correspondence. Dated Dec. 7, 1945. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To Laurence Petran. Telegram. Dated Dec.17, 1946. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Untitled manuscript, photocopy. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. UC Biography, holograph. Purchased from Scientific Library Service. (Box 1)
- London Symphony Orchestra. Program. Dated Nov. 8, 1965 at the Royal Festival Hall. (Box 1)
- Radulescu, Michael. Comparison of Organ Variations by Bach and Schoenberg. Notice of lecture-recital. Schoenberg Hall. Dated Jan. 7, 1971. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Five Pieces for Orchestra. L.A. Philharmonic performance. Newspaper review. From L.A. Times, dated Mar. 5, 1966. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Gurrelieder. L.A. Philharmonic performance. Newspaper review. From L.A. Times, dated Mar. 23, 1968. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Performing Arts (V. 2, no.3). Performing Gurre-Lieder. Journal. Dated March 1968. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Catalog of works. Belmont Music. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Catalog of works. In German. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Gertrud. Newspaper clipping. From The Guardian, dated Jun. 23, 1965. (Box 1)
- Vosper, Robert. To Gordon Stone. Correspondence. Dated Dec. 5, 1962. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To Walter R. Hashning. Photograph, b&w, inscribed. San Francisco. Dated March 1935. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. To Donald L. Hashning. Photograph, b&w, inscribed. San Francisco. Dated March 1935. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Photograph, b&w. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Photograph, b&w. (Box 1)
- Schoenberg, Arnold. Photograph, b&w. (Box 1)
- UCLA Composers Council flyer, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Musical examples for classes in polyphony/counterpoint, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folders 2-5)
  Scope and Contents
  Some pages are annotated or have handwritten notes.
- White, Alice van Hesse, 1938-1939 and 2001 (Box 2, Folders 6-9)
  Includes White's reminisences of being a student of Schoenberg's from 1936-1939, along with some of her student compositions annotated by Schoenberg.